Guide to the William Weaver Papers, 1809-1885
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
William Weaver papers 1809-1885
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Weaver, William, 1780-1863
3,387 Items 4.0 linear feet
Ironmaster and pioneer in scientific agriculture, from Goshen (Rockbridge Co.), Va.
Correspondence and business papers of the owner of the Bath Iron Works, Buffalo Forge, Va., containing information about the iron industry in antebellum Virginia, the use of slaves as industrial laborers, life among Weaver's workers, the supply of iron to the Confederate government, the iron industry in the Confederacy, and industrial conditions in Virginia during Reconstruction. Personal correspondence discusses the progress of the war in Virginia and Confederate politics.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Weaver Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1956 to 1957.
Biographical Note
Ironmaster and pioneer in scientific agriculture, from Goshen (Rockbridge Co.), Va.
Collection Overview
Collection contains business papers of William Weaver (1781-1863?), owner of the Bath Iron Works, dealing with the iron industry in Virginia, and containing information on types of items in demand; collection of debts; prices of iron, land, crops, and livestock; the hiring and use of slave labor; and diet, clothing, wages, and prices of slaves. Included are several lists of slaves, with a brief physical description and comments on their reliability as workers. Personal correspondence discusses cholera in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Baltimore, Maryland, 1832; smallpox in Lexington, Virginia; typhoid in Texas, 1853; the activities and pension of a Revolutionary soldier; state and national politics, especially under Andrew Jackson; the completion of the canal from the mouth of the Brazos River to Galveston, Texas, 1853; the election of 1860; vigilance committees in Virginia; the use of substitutes; troop movements through Lynchburg and Richmond, Virginia; food prices; the death of Thomas Jonathan Jackson; and the iron industry during the war. Letters, 1861-1863, from John Letcher (1813-1884), U. S. congressman, 1851-1859, and governor of Virginia during the Civil War, discuss his message to the Virginia General Assembly concerning state and Confederate affairs in 1861; rumors; the failure of the legislature to provide replacement troops; military actions at Gordonsville and Fredericksburg, Virginia; various Confederate and Union generals; the unlikelihood of European intervention; military activity in North Carolina; and public opinion in the North.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bath Iron Works (Buffalo Forge, Va.)
Industries -- Confederate States of America
Iron and steel workers -- Virginia
Iron industry and trade -- Confederate States of America
Iron industry and trade -- Virginia
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)--Virginia
Slavery -- Virginia
Industries -- Virginia
Confederate States of America -- Politics and government
Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- William Weaver Papers, 1809-1885, (11 boxes)
  - Papers, 1809-1829 Aug. (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1829 Sept.-1830 (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1831-1832 (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1833-1835 (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1836-1860 (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1861-1869 (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1870-1874 (Box 7)
  - Papers, 1875-1885, undated. (Box 8)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1816-1830s (Box 9)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1840s-1860s (Box 10)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1870s (Box 11)